Guide to the Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington family papers
1679-1855
1730-1790
OSB MSS 138
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.65
(19 boxes) + 17 broadside items
The papers document the West Indian portions of the economic fortunes and political career of the sugar planter and politician Ralph Payne, first Baron Lavington.
Lavington, Ralph Payne, baron, 1738-1807
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Oversize and Parchment Oversize material in boxes 17-18 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. In some cases, conservation work to an item may be necessary before the item can be consulted. Restricted Fragile in box 19 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been substituted in the main files.
Associated Materials
Related material may be found in the Lavington Papers: Stuart Documents and in the Osborn Files, located at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library; the Payne Family Papers, located at the University of British Columbia; several collections in the British Library and the National Library of Ireland; and the Limerick University Library. Several items relating to Lord Lavington are cataloged in The Beinecke Lesser Antilles Collection at Hamilton College by Samuel J. and Penelope R. O. Hough (University Press of Florida, 1994)
RALPH PAYNE, BARON LAVINGTON (1739-1807)
Ralph Payne was born in Basseterre, St. Kitts, in 1739, the surviving son of Ralph Payne (d. 1763), chief justice of St. Kitts, and his first wife Alice Carlisle, the only surviving child and heiress of the Antiguan planter Francis Carlisle.
Like many of the West Indian elite, Payne divided his time between England, especially London, and the Caribbean plantations from which he derived his wealth and power. Educated at Christ's Hospital, Payne returned to Antigua in 1759, where he was promptly elected to the House of Assembly and unanimously voted Speaker of the House.
Payne returned to England in 1762 and embarked on a lengthy and expensive Grand Tour of Europe. In 1767 he married Françoise Lambertina Kölbel, daughter of Henry, Baron Kölbel of Saxony; she was a close friend of Queen Charlotte. Shortly after his marriage, Payne entered English politics, and was M.P. for Shaftesbury from 1768 until 1771, when he was made Knight of the Order of the Bath and set sail for Antigua as the newly-appointed Governor-General of the Leeward Islands.
Payne was popular with the plantation owners. He supported Lord North's government in its struggles with the North American colonists, reporting in 1774 that his islands were free of "mischievous sparks of the Continental flame." He was the first governor in over fifty years to visit every one of the Leeward Islands, after the "Great Hurricane" of 1772. (At the time, the colony consisted of Antigua, Barbuda, the British Virgin Islands, Montserrat, St. Christopher's (St. Kitts), Nevis, Anguilla and Dominica.) He also patronized the artist Thomas Hearne. In 1775, the Paynes left for England "to reestablish Lady Payne's health," and the Assembly petitioned for his speedy return and presented him with a diamond-encrusted sword as a token of their affection. Payne was to remain in England for the next twenty-four years.
He spent many years in various elective and appointive offices, becoming a supporter of Fox after 1780. Payne and his wife also became known for their elaborate parties, despite the rumored unhappiness of their marriage. In 1788 he traveled again on the Continent, and conducted secret but unsuccessful negotiations with Charlotte, Duchess of Albany over the possible return of the Stuart crown jewels to England.
Payne, whose wealth was declining rapidly due to his lavish spending and to the sharp decline of sugar profits after the American Revolution, seceded from the Whig Club and allied with William Pitt and Henry Dundas. In fact, the dinner at which Dundas and Lord Loughborough first broached the idea of an alliance between Pitt and the Duke of Portland was held at his Grafton Street house. His reward for changing parties followed quickly; he was created Baron Lavington of Lavington in the Irish peerage in October 1795.
In 1799 he was re-appointed Governor-General of the Leeward Islands, and arrived in Antigua in August, 1801. He moved into the just-completed Government House, and remained on that island until his death in August, 1807. Payne was buried on Carlisles, his Antigua plantation. His estate was thoroughly encumbered by debts, mortgages, and liferents, and his widow was left so poor that the Antiguan assembly voted her a pension of L 300 a year "in affection and esteem." She returned soon after to England, and died at Hampton Court Palace in 1830. See "Payne, Ralph, Baron Lavington" in the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography (Oxford, 2004) for further information.
Scope and Contents
The Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington Papers document the West Indian portions of the economic fortunes and political career of the sugar planter and politician Ralph Payne, first Baron Lavington. The researcher will also find the papers of value in the study of the history of the Caribbean sugar trade, including documentation of land and slave ownership and estate management in the West Indies. While the record of Payne's holdings is far from complete, his papers reveal the dense networks of family and patronage connections that operated in the Caribbean colonies in the later eighteenth century. The papers span the dates 1689-1855, but the bulk of the material dates from 1730 to 1790. The collection is organized into six series: Correspondence; Political and Governmental Papers; Land and Plantation Records; Payne Family Personal Estate Papers; Other Business Papers; and Accounts, Bills and Receipts. Boxes 16-17 contain Oversize material. Oversize Broadside Material is housed in a separate location.
Administration of estates; Inheritance and succession -- Great Britain; Plantation life; Plantation owners; Seven Years' War, 1756-1763 -- Naval operations; Slave trade -- Great Britain; Slaveholders; Slavery -- Great Britain; Sugar trade -- Great Britain; Antigua; Great Britain -- Colonies -- Administration; Great Britain -- History -- 1714-1837; Nevis; Saint Croix (United States Virgin Islands); Saint Kitts; Tortola (British Virgin Islands); Adye, Stephen Payne, -1794; Byam, Edward; Johnson, Godschall; Lavington, Ralph Payne, baron, 1738-1807; Ottley, Drewry, fl. 1750-1780; Payne family; Payne, Ralph, d. 1763; Payne, Stephen, d. 1772?; Payne-Gallwey, Stephen; Willett, Ralph, 1719-1795
- Correspondence, 1741-1801; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is organized into four subseries: Sir Ralph Payne (d. 1763?), Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington (1739-1808), Stephen Payne (d. 1772?), and Third Party Correspondence. Within each subseries letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with unidentified letters placed at the end. The series includes correspondence of Ralph Payne and of various family members, including his father and his uncle, Stephen Payne. The first subseries, Sir Ralph Payne (d. 1763) contains mostly single business letters from overseers, tenants, debtors, and sugar factors to the father of Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington. The letters of Alexander Cooper, who was the elder Payne's partner in the establishment of a sugar plantation on St. Croix, contain precise details about that operation, covering everything from a lack of copper for boilers and the high price of salt beef to an epidemic among the slaves. A 1753 letter describes the practice of giving sick slaves "their liberty" on the Spanish Main. Other topics in this subseries include the difficulty of collecting debts; the shipment of sugar to New York and London; and plantation conditions. Discussion of individual slaves and slave management practices occurs throughout the letters. W. Thomas's comprehensive offer to sell his estate to Payne includes a request to exclude several slaves from the sale at "my wife's desire that the family shall not be separated." The second subseries, Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington, primarily consists of brief business notes concerning bills of exchange, letters of credit, and appointments. Most correspondents are represented by fewer than five letters. There are two folders of lengthy letters from Edward Jones, who was apparently overseer of Payne's plantations on Antigua, containing details of many slave sales; sugar prices and production difficulties; the effects of the naval war on shipping in the Leeward Islands; and other business matters. Several 1799 letters discuss the suitability of Government House as Payne's official residence and other preparations for his arrival in Antigua. Folders 65-70 contain the letters of Godschall Johnson, another Antigua planter with substantial business interests in England who spent years in London. Most of these letters were written while Payne was traveling on the Continent in 1787-88, and contain reports requested by Payne on his sugar plantations, shipping arrangements and finances; information on bills of exchange, annuities, mortgages, and other business dealings among members of the interconnected Payne, Ottley, Willett, Adye, and Payne-Gallwey families of St. Kitts and Antigua; and some personal news. The Stephen Payne subseries includes a group of lengthy letters from bibliophile and St. Kitts native Ralph Willett, located in folders 101-112. Written during the 1760s, the letters document Willett's extensive business interests on St. Kitts, particularly the problems of absentee estate management, including sugar production, plantation maintenance, unreliable overseers, and chronically indebted renters. Willett also sends news of and comments on various relatives, including Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington himself. A March 25, 1763 letter, written shortly after Sir Ralph Payne's death, points out that his son "makes, for a young man, a great sacrifice in leaving England" to manage his inheritance on St. Kitts. Willett's unsuccessful attempts to arrange a marriage for the dowerless cousin Nancy Payne are also discussed in detail, as are various business dealings, inheritances, and debts among Willett's family connections. The remainder of the subseries consists of mostly routine business letters addressed to Stephen Payne, who was an uncle of Ralph Payne and one of his agents and accountants. At least two of the 1763 letters mention Ralph Payne's recent death. Third Party Correspondence contains letters to recipients other than the main members of the Payne family. They concern business and legal matters. The letters of Judith Butler Dunbar concern the settlement of a relative's estate.
  - Sir Ralph Payne (d. 1763?)
    - Alford, James, 1741 Mar 9 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Banister, John, 1749 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Barclay, Andrew, 1755 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      With: 2 1755 invoices from the New York firm
    - Barrett, Onslow, 1762 Aug 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Blake, S., 1762 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bolans & Macmahon, 1749 Mar 21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bourryau & Spooner, 1751 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brodbelt, John, 1755, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Brodbelt, Richard, 1747 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brown, Francis, 1747 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Burnett, George, 1758, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Butler, James, 1759 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Also signed by Thomas Hooke
    - Coleman & Lucas, 1758, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Colhoun, Robert, 1756, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cooper, Alexander, 1753-1758 (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
    - Cooper, George, 1760 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cooper, John, 1759 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Fahie, George, 1761, 1762 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Farren, Frederick, 1755 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Farren, Josias, 1758 Dec 29 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Frankland, John, 1750, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - Graham, George, 1757 Jul 15 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Hamm, John, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Honey, William, 1754-1755 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Irwin, Andrew, 1760-1761 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Laroche, James, 1762 Feb 11 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Concerning sales of Ralph Payne's sugar; addressed to Mrs. Ottley
    - Low, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Mathew, Richard, 1762 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Mills, Peter M., undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Molineux, C., undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Newton, William, 1755, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Ottley, Drewry, 1756 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Ottley, Lucretia, 1760 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Payne, Joseph, 1750 Apr 27, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Payne, Ralph, 1752-1758 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Draft copies of four business letters
    - Perrott, Andrew, 1758 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      With: Bond to Robert Nutter, 1758 May 15
    - Phipps & Leigh, 1762 Apr 17 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Concerning deaths of Dominick Trant and his son James
      Signed: Con.t Phipps; Geo. Leigh
    - Pocock, George?, 1749 Jan 31 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Protheroe, Philip, 1750 Apr 27 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Sharpe, Henry, 1758 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Sharpe, John, 1753 Apr, Jun (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Stead, Benjamin, 1759 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Stewart, Judith, 1762 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Concerning the estate of Governor Heyliger of St. Eustatius
    - Sutton, ?, 1758 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Tannatt, Edmund, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Thomas, W., 1747 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Concerning his desire to exclude several slaves from a proposed estate sale
      Accompanied by "A Copy of my former proposalls" concerning a 1745 mortgage
    - Trant, Dominick, 1762 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Also addressed to Stephen Payne
    - Turner, Robert, 1750 Apr 18 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Wardrop, William, 1750 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Warner, Thomas, 1754 Oct 19
    - Woodley, William, 1762 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington (1738-1807)
    - Audain, Anne Payne, 1781 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Audain, John, 1777-1787 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Browne, Jackson, 1787 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Desborough, Mr., 1797? (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Feuilleteau, William, 1787 Feb 22 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Gallwey, Stephen Payne, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Georges, W., undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Hamilton, Mr., 1776 Apr 19 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Johnson, Godschall, 1786-1798, undated (Box 2, Folder 65-70)
    - Jones, Edward, 1797-1801 (Box 2, Folder 71-72)
      Includes: 2 copies of business correspondence from Jones to others
    - Knapp, Edward, 1786 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Lavington, Ralph Payne, Baron, 1759-1799 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      Retained drafts of 12 business letters
    - Maitland & Boddington, 1759 Mar 26, undated (Box 2, Folder 75-76)
    - Mannings & Vaughan, 1786 Dec 18 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Neave & Willett, 1772-1777 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Ottley, Drewry, 1782-1788, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Ottley, Mary, 1786? (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Pearce, Charles, 1771, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Pownall, Thomas?, 1777 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Somers, Mr., 1790 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Stanley, John, 1771-1773 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Stephens, William, 1797 Mar 28 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Warner, Thomas, 1772 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 86)
      With: letter to Warner concerning Drewry Ottley's lack of a marriage settlement, undated
    - Wilett, Mr., undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Willett, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Willett, Ralph, 1776 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Woodley, William, 1797, undated (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Stephen Payne (d. 1772?)
    - Baker, Mo., 1748 Aug 9 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - Cottle, Thomas, 1765 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 92)
      With: enclosed letter from John Willett to Cottle, 1765 Feb 6
    - Dunbar, Charles, 1740-1748 (Box 2, Folder 93-95)
      Collector of the Customs
    - Esdaile, James, 1764 Apr 26 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Mathew, Janett, 1763 Mar 10 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      Mentions "Mr. Payne's death"
    - Mills, John, 1764 Apr, May (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Ottley, Drewry, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Payne, Stephen, 1763, 1764 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      Retained drafts. The 1763 letter mentions the death of "Mr. Payne"
    - Willett, Ralph, 1762-1769 (Box 3, Folder 101-112)
    - Woodley, William, 1762, 1764 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Unidentified, 1762, undated (Box 3, Folder 114-115)
  - Third-Party Correspondence
    - Dunbar, Judith Butler, 1759 (Box 3, Folder 116-117)
    - Holt, Frances, 1759 Jan 6 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Gordon, George, 1756, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Keige, James, 1775 Jan 23 (Box 3, Folder 120)
    - Mills, John and Thomas, 1758-1759 (Box 3, Folder 121-122)
    - Seton, James, 1798 Jul 26 (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Willett, Ralph?, 1779, undated (Box 3, Folder 124-125)
    - Unidentified, 1760-1773 (Box 3, Folder 126-127)
    - Empty covers and labels, undated (Box 3, Folder 128)
- Political and Governmental Papers, 1724-1812; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II, Political and Governmental Records, is organized into four chronological and topical subseries: Member of the Assembly (1759-1761); First Governorship of the Leeward Islands (1771-1775); Tortola Dispute Papers; and Second Governorship of the Leeward Islands (1799-1807). The series documents the West Indian portion of Ralph Payne, Baron Lavington's political career. It contains no records related to his service in the British Parliament. The first subseries, Member of the Assembly, contains several documents from Payne's first office holding as a member of the House of Assembly. These relate to the dissatisfaction of the Leeward islanders with the British military's abandonment of an attack on Martinique in 1759, and include "A Transliteration from the French of a Letter from the Inhabitants of a Neighboring Island to ------." This is a satire in which the inhabitants of Martinique supposedly thank Sir John Moore for relieving them against the interests of Great Britain, and rehearse all of the Leeward Islanders' complaints. There are also documents relating to the official inquiry into Moore's conduct, apparently abandoned after his successful capture of Guadeloupe in March of 1760. The second subseries, "First Governorship of the Leeward Islands (1771-1776) primarily concerns Payne's departure from Antigua on a leave in 1775 and include the official grant of his leave by George III, a copy of his farewell speech to the Legislature and the legislature's petition for his return. Folder 134 contains a copy of "Queries Relating to his Majesty's Islands in America," a 1773 survey sent to Caribbean governors by Lord Dartmouth. Tortola Dispute Papers, housed in folders 138-145, document parts of a frequent type of conflict over land ownership and property rights in the Caribbean colonies, stemming from what Lavington refers to as "the usurpation of property arising from the lawless state of the country." In this case, the Governor's demand that the Tortolans produce their title deeds and letters patent resulted in a long and bitter dispute over the existence and authenticity of such documentation, as rival claims and duplicate title documents, some apparently forged or issued in error, were entered into evidence. The documents include Lavington's statement concerning his conduct in the matter, particularly in the case of John Fahie, and a letter from Fahie denouncing the Tortolans and the Assembly of the Virgin Islands and adding details of the islanders' fight against the title demand.
  - Member of the Assembly (1759-1761)
    - Dispute over Commodore Moore's Conduct
      - "Mr. Pickering agent for Barbados's letter to the Committee concerning their Remonstrance against Commodore Moore", 1759 Nov 21 (Box 4, Folder 129)
      - Letters copy concerning Moore's conduct and the action by the Assembly of Barbados, undated (Box 4, Folder 130)
      - "A Translation from the French of a letter from the Inhabitants of a neighboring Island", undated (Box 4, Folder 131)
      - Newspaper clipping discussing Moore's conduct (incomplete), 1760 Feb 18 (Box 4, Folder 132)
        From the Boston Evening Post
      - ALS from John Moore to the Committee concerning the convoy, 1760 Mar 3 (Box 4, Folder 133)
      - Questions and draft answers concerning Commodore Moore's conduct, [1760]
  - First Governorship of the Leeward Islands (1771-1775)
    - "Additional Instructions", 1772 Jul 1
      Concerning the legislature of St. Christopher's; signature and seal of King George III
    - "Queries Relating to His Majesty's Islands in America", 1773 Jul 5 (Box 4, Folder 134)
      With: copy of circular letter from Lord Dartmouth
    - Leave of Absence; signature and seal of King George III, 1774 Dec 10 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - "Answer upon the Presentation of the Sword from the Legislature of Antigua", [1775?]
    - Letter of petition from the General Assembly of Antigua to King George III, [1775] (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Other papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Tortola Dispute Papers
    - Labels, undated (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - Copy of Robert Kenny's patent from Queen Anne, 1713 May 20, undated (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - Richard Downing's patent from King George I, 1724 Jun 1
    - Petition of the Lieutenant Governor and Assembly of the Virgin Islands concerning Tortola, 1774 May 7
    - "Copy of a Letter from Mr. Fahie", 1774 May 8
      Concerning the Tortola Assembly
    - Letter from John Fahie concerning his 1774 May 8 letter, 1774 Jun (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - Petition of John Downing Junior and others concerning Tortola, 1774 Aug 2
    - George III letter patent to John Downing Junior (copy), 1774 Oct 16 (Box 4, Folder 141)
    - "Letters from Mr. Warner &c about Tortola", 1774-1775 (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - "Memorial of John Downing Junior Esq.", 1776 Nov 20
    - Lord Lavington's response to the Memorial of John Downing Junior, [1777] (Box 4, Folder 143-144)
      With: ALS from Alexander Wedderburn concerning the Memorial, n.d.
    - Letter from John Fahie concerning the Memorial (2 copies), 1778 Apr 29 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Second Governorship of the Leeward Islands (1799-1807)
    - "Account of Office Fees Received by Mr. Thomson....1799...1801", 1804 (Box 4, Folder 146-147)
    - Letter copy from the Office of Ordnance requesting payment for guns and stores for Antigua, 1805 Feb 3 (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - Letter of thanks from the Council of St. Christopher, [1806?] (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - Anglia. Account of the Right Honourable Lord Lavington, late Governor of the Leeward Islands from 14 February 1801 to 21 July 1807, 1812 Feb 1 (Box 4, Folder 149)
      Parchment roll
- Land and Plantation Records, 1689-1855; Series III; 1.67; (4 boxes)